The John H. Ferguson MD Collection
Archives and Special Collections at the SUNY Upstate Health Sciences Library
The John H. Ferguson MD Collection
1949-2006
SUNY Upstate Medical University 766 Irving Avenue Syracuse, NY 13210
Ferguson, John H. and unknown
1.3 linear feet
This collection contains the papers of John H. Ferguson (1902-1978), who graduated from Syracuse University College of Medicine in 1926 and later taught at the university, chairing both the Pathology and Medical Jurisprudence departments. The collection has five series: Chronological Calendar, History Report to the Committee of Board of Trustees, Subject Files, Memorabilia, and Photographs.
FIC2018.0003
Biographical Note
Born in Elmira Heights, New York, John H. Ferguson (1902-1978) received his undergraduate degree from Syracuse University and his M.D. from the Syracuse University College of Medicine in 1926. Shortly after his graduation, Ferguson was appointed as an instructor of Pathology in 1927, made Assistant Professor in 1929, Professor in 1942, and Chairman in 1950. He also taught courses in the Medical Jurisprudence Department until it was absorbed by the Department of Public Health and Preventative Medicine in 1954. In addition to his teaching contributions, Ferguson played key roles in the future of the institution. In 1933, he helped to plan and design the Basic Sciences Building. In the late 1940’s, he compiled a report for a State Committee, persuading them to transform the Syracuse University College of Medicine to what is now SUNY Upstate Medical University. He taught at SUNY Upstate Medical University until his retirement in 1968. In addition to his contributions to medical education, Ferguson was the Onondaga County Necrotomist from 1927-1950.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the papers of John H. Ferguson (1902-1978), who graduated from Syracuse University College of Medicine in 1926 and later taught at the university, chairing both the Pathology and Medical Jurisprudence departments. There are five series in this collection.
Chronological Calendar: This manuscript compiles a history of SUNY Upstate Medical University, from its origins as Geneva Medical College in 1834 and its assimilation into the State University of New York system in 1950. Chapters of the manuscript are largely based on departments (administration, libraries, secretaries, pathology, anatomy, biochemistry, family medicine, jurisprudence, etc.). Each department is then organized chronologically, highlighting chairmen, deans, and key administrative figures from the creation of the department until around 1968. Almost every figure listed and described by Ferguson is accompanied by a photograph. Individuals may appear in more than one chapter, as they were the head of multiple departments. Additions and revisions to selected chapters were added in the 1980s and early 2000s by unknown contributors.
History Report to the Committee to the Board of Trustees: This document argues the case for the State to purchase Syracuse University Medical College in order to establish their upstate medical college. Ferguson provides a narrative history of Syracuse University Medical College, including photographs of floor plans, the campus, and internal views of classrooms. He also provides information about the library, School of Public Health Nursing, costs and incomes, local hospitals, relationships to local industries (such as Bristol Laboratories), and the future of the College. The report is a total of 51 pages.
Subject files: This file includes newspaper clippings of Ferguson’s obituaries, a copy of his dedication in the 1965 Auricle, a copy of Ferguson’s curriculum vitae (circa 1950), and a letter from John H. Ferguson Jr.
Memorabilia: This file includes awards Ferguson received upon his retirement.
Photographs: There are sixteen black-and-white portrait photographs and eight negatives of John H. Ferguson, most likely his faculty portraits.
Arrangement of the Collection
The John H. Ferguson MD Collection is mostly in original order, with additions to the Chronological Calendar in the 1980s and early 2000s.
Related Material
There is an interview conducted by John H. Ferguson with Dean Weiskotten in the Herman G. Weiskotten MD PhD Papers.
Subject and Genre Headings
Ferguson, John H. (John Howard), 1902-1978; Geneva Medical College; Medical education; SUNY Upstate Medical University; Syracuse (N.Y.); Syracuse University, College of Medicine
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Unknown.
Inventory
- Chronological Calendar
  - Title page, index, and list of updates., 1968; 1985; undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General., 1968; undated; 3 folders (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Appendix to General Section., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Deans and Presidents., 1968; undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    The following individuals are included in this folder with a photograph and biography unless otherwise noted. Names appear in chronological order:
    Frederick Hyde, Henry Darwin Didama, Gaylord P. Clark, John L. Heffron, Herman G. Weiskotten, William R. Williard (only biography), Wilfred W. Westerfeld, Carlyle F. Jacobsen, Julius B. Richmond, Lewis W. Bluemle Jr., Richard P. Schmidt, George F. Reed, Donald C. Goodman, John B. Henry
  - Secretaries., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Abby Bond, Mary A. Barker, Louise Leonard, Lucy Pelton Faigle, Genevieve Mahan Rowlingson, Mary Burkhard Evans, Maxine King
  - Administration., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    James H. Abbott, Augustus J. Carroll, David A. Sinclair, Francis J. Wozniak, Joseph K. Hill, Kirby A. Vosburg, Davis G. Johnson, Donald A. Boulton, Walter Wiggins, Lee Walton, William A. Harris, Richard Muller, Stella Zimmer, Louis Georgianna, Nickolas Apgar, Joyce Berman Goldberg, Julia Hammock, Gary Bishop, Ellen Cook Jacobsen, Donald C. Samson, Albert G. Boeck, Anna Halsted, Betty N. Kisil, David N. Watts, William Mueller, Edward Toner, John Maines, Ward Mackey, Hobart Newton, Raymond McPhilmy, Jean Fancher, Richard Drayer, Thomas Ranger, Sam Martin
  - Library., 1968; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    The following individuals are included in this folder with a photograph. Names appear in chronological order:
    Ruth Bielby, Clark Rumsey, Stanley E. Truelson, Irwin H. Pizner, Evelyn L. Hoey
  - Anatomy., 1968; undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    John Towler, John Van Duyn, Gaylord P. Clark (only biography), Scott Owen, George M. Price, Harold D. Senior, Henry W. Stiles, Philip B. Armstrong, David G. Whitlock, Chester L. Yntema, Donald C. Goodman, Elinore J. Spring-Mills, Larry F. Lemanski
  - Biochemistry., 1968; undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Reverend John J. Brown, John Towler, William Manlius Smith, Charles A. Covell, George A. Hanford, Gustave M. Meyer, Ernest Noble Pattee, Robert K. Brewer, Wilfred W. Westerfeld, William R. Ruegamer, Anthony N. Martonosi (only biography), John Clint Elwood, Richard L. Cross
  - Physiology., 1968; undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Nelson Nivison, Reuben C. Hanchett, Horace D. Babcock, Lucien M. Underwood, Gaylord P. Clark, Frank P. Knowlton, Robert F. Pitts, Gordon K. Moe, James Preston
  - Pharmacology., 1968; undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Otis J. Burt, George R. Metcalf, William H. Dunlap, John L. Heffron, Reuben C. Hanchett, William A. Curtin, Henry B. Doust, Marion S. Dooley, Allan D. Bass, Alfred Farah, Jay Tepperman, Helen Tepperman, Irwin M. Weiner, Jose Jalife
  - Microbiology., 1968; undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Leverett Dale Bristol, Oliver Wendell Holmes Mitchell, Orren D. Chapman, Justus F. Mueller, Paul F. Wehrle, George G. Holz, Robert M. Dougherty
  - Pathology., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Nelson Nivison, A. Clifford Mercer, William H. May, Halbert S. Steensland, Herman G. Weiskotten, J. Howard Ferguson, Rolla B. Hill, Gerald B. Gordon (only photograph), Frederick R. Davey, W. Dewey Alsever, William A. Groat, Ellery G. Allen, Eugene L. Lozner, John B. Henry
  - Medicine., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Hiram N. Eastman, Henry Darwin Didama, Henry L. Elsner, I. Harris Levy, Edward C. Reifenstein Sr., Richard H. Lyons, Paul A. Bunn, William J. Williams
  - Neurology., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Harvey B. Wilbur, J.C. Carson, Richard H. Hutchings, Hersey G. Locke, Wardner D. Ayer, Eugene N. Boudreau, Philip E. Duffy, Giblert S. Ross, Carl J. Croslet, Burk Jubelt
  - Dermatology., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    J. Otis Burt, William H. Dunlap, Henry Clay Baum, Henry A. MacGruer, Lopo DeMello, Schuyler P. Richmond, Leon H. Griggs
  - Preventive Medicine., 1967; 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Nelson Nivison, Alfred Mercer, William H. Mills (only biography), Fred M. Meader, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Clealand A. Sargent, William A. Brumfield, Harry A. Feldman, Richard P. Oates
  - Rehabilitation., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Charles A. Covell, Alfred A. Mercer, Jacob J. Levy, Lee A. Hadley, Thomas E. Walsh, George M. Raus, Leo Jivoff
  - Surgery., 1968; 1978; 1992; undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Frederick Hyde, John Van Duyn, Nathan Jacobson, David M. Totman, Edward S. Van Duyn, Albert G. Swift, Arthur B. Raffl, Robert O. Gregg, C. Barber Mueller, Lloyd S. Rogers
  - Anesthesiology., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    John J. Buettner, Joseph Delmonico, Allen B. Dobkin, Howard L. Zauder, Enrico Camporesi
  - Orthopedic Surgery., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Edward S. Van Duyn, Ralph R. Fitch, Clarence E. Coon, Richard S. Farr, Roscoe D. Severance, John B. Stevens, James B. Wray, David G. Murray, Hansen Yuan
  - Urology., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Alfred M. Wose, Thomas F. Laurie, Leo E. Gibson, Francis O. Harbach, Otto M. Lilien, Zahni N. Makhuli, James Keith Light
  - Neurosurgery., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Howard G. Case, Arthur E. Ecker, Stanley Batkin, Robert B. King, Charles Hodge
  - Otolaryngology., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Charles E. Rider, John Van Duyn, William H. Dunlap, Nathan Jacobson, Frank W. Marlow, Thomas H. Halsted, George S. Britten, Frederick J. O'Conner, Mortimer G. Brown, Gordon D. Hoople, Harry A. Rubenstein, David W. Brewer, Alfred W. Doust, George F. Reed, Richard Raymond Gacek
  - Ophthalmology., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Charles E. Rider, John Van Duyn, Frank W. Marlow, David F. Gillette, Harold H. Joy, Franklin R. Webster, James L. McGraw, John Hoepner
  - Pediatrics., 1968; undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Wilfred W. Porter, J. Otis Burt, William T. Plant, A. Clifford Mercer, Edward Judson Wynkoop, Brewster C. Doust, Tyree C. Wyatt, Julius B. Richmond, Sterling D. Garrard, Mary Louise [Voorhees], Frank Aram Oski, Warren Grupe
  - Obstetrics and Gynecology., 1968; undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Wilfred W. Porter, Henry B. Allen, William D. Hinsdale, Albert S. Hotaling, Eugene W. Belknap, Henry W. Schoeneck, Robert E. L. Nesbitt, Edward C. Hughes, Aaron B. Miller, George B. Broad, Thomas P. Farmer, Nathan P. Sears, Chester E. Clark, Michael S. Baggish
  - Psychiatry., 1968; undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Harvey B. Wilbur, J. C. Carson, Richard H. Hutchings, Hersey G. Locke, Wardner D. Ayer, Eugene N. Boudreau, Harry E. Steckel, Edward J. Stainbrook, Marc H. Hollender, David B. Robinson, Donald Oken, Sidney A. Orgel, Leslie Franklin Major
  - Radiology., 1968; undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Charles A. Covell, A. Clifford Mercer, Clarence E. Coon, Donald S. Childs, Foster C. Rulison, Clayton H. Hale, Paul A. Riemenschneider, John G. McAfee, Stephen A. Kieffer
  - Medical Jurisprudence., 1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    William T. Plant, J. Gilbert Justin, Martin A. Knapp, Ceylon H. Lewis, William S. Andrews, William Avery Groat, J. Howard Ferguson
  - Health Related Professions., 1968; undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    John Herbert Morrison, G. Bruce Dearing, Mary Jane Brennan Schneider, Donald Charles Goodman (only biography)
  - Emergency Medicine., undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    John McCabe
  - Family Practice., 1981; undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Francis S. Calvia, L. Thomas Wolff, John DeSimone, Macaran Baird
  - Education Communications., undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    James S. Waldron
- 1949 History Report to the Committee of Board of Trustees
  - 1949 History Report to the Committee of Board of Trustees., 1971; undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Subject Files
  - Biographical information., 1934; 1978; undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards., 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Photographs
  - undated (Box 3, Folder 12)